

RESEARCH SCIENTIST · RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSIC

Department of Physics, 1110 West Green Street, Urbana, Illinois, 61801-3003, US

□ (+217) 819-9458 | ▼ruizm@illinois.edu | ★miltonruizm.github.io

Summary_

Research Scientist in the Department of Physics at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign studying compact objects mergers in magnetized environments, including binary black holes in gaseous disks, black hole–neutron star binaries, and neutron star binaries. The ultimate goal is to predict and correlate observable gravitational-waves and electromagnetic signatures from these events. Also, strongly interested in alternative theories of gravity and in mathematical aspects of numerical relativity.

Work Experience _____

Research Scientist Urbana, Illinois

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT URBANA-CHAMPAIGN (UIUC)

Aug 2016 -

Postdoctoral Research Associate

CPAN Postdoctoral Research Associate

Urbana, Illinois

2013 - 2016

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UIUC

SPANISH NATIONAL CENTER FOR PARTICLE, ASTROPARTICLE AND NUCLEAR PHYSICS, UNIVERSITAT DE LES ILLES BALEARS

Palma de Mallorca, Spain 2011 - 2013

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Jena, Germany

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT, FRIEDRICH-SCHILLER-UNIVERSITÄT

2009 - 2010

Education

Ph.D. Physics

Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL AUTONOMOUS UNIVERSITY OF MEXICO (UNAM)

April, 2009

• Dissertation: Axial symmetry, Gravitational Waves and Boundary Conditions

Advisor: Miguel Alcubierre Field: Numerical Relativity

Master of Science (Physics)

Mexico City, Mexico

UNAM

June, 2006

Bachelor of Science (Physics)

Bogota, Colombia

NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

June, 2003

• Dissertation: Exact Solution of the Einstein's Equations

Major Collaborations _____

LISA Consortium:

Numerical Relativity & Analytical Relativity – Waveform modeling for MBHBs group

Urbana, Illinois

July 2018 -

Honors & Awards

2015-2016 **Fellowship for Basic Research**, Colombian Ministry of Education 2011-2013 **Fellowship for advance research**, Spanish National Center for Astroparticle and Nuclear Physics

2005-2009 **Fellowship for PhD studies**, Mexican Ministry of Education

2000-2004 Fellowship for B.S. studies, Colombian Ministry of Education

Bogota, Colombia Madrid, Spain Mexico City, Mexico Bogota, Colombia **Research Stays**.

Friedrich-Schiller-Universität
Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut

Jena, Germany

June 2008

Louisiana State University

Louisiana, US

CENTER FOR COMPUTATIONAL AND TECHNOLOGY

June - Aug 2006

Teaching Experience

Guest Lecturer Graduate level

INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER

Bucaramanga, Colombia, 2015

Jena, Germany, 2010

· Lecture: Advanced Topics in General Relativity

Teaching Assistant Undergraduate level

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut, Friedrich-Schiller-Universität

• Lecture: Numerische Relativitaetstheorie (Numerical Relativity)

Teaching Assistant Undergraduate level

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut, Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena, Germany, 2009

• Lecture: Allgemeine Relativitaetstheorie (General Relativity)

Teaching Assistant/Grader Undergraduate level

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico, 2006-2007

• Lecture: General Relativity

Teaching Assistant/Grader Graduate level

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

• Lecture: Classical Mechanics

Teaching Assistant/Grader Graduate level

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM
Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

• Lecture: Quantum Mechanics

Student Advising

2016-2018 **Abid Khan, graduate student**, UIUC *Urbana, Illinois*

2015 - Lunan Sun, graduate student, UIUC
 2018 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Guangkuo Liu, Minh Nguyen, Kyle Nelli, UIUC
 Urbana, Illinois
 Urbana, Illinois

2019 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Samuel Qunell, Michael Mudd, UIUC Urbana, Illinois

Seminar and Conference Organizer

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar

Weekly Seminar Jan 2017 - Dec 2017

First Symposium of Relativistic Astrophysics

Bucaramanga, Colombia

Industrial University of Santander

June 10-12, 2015

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar

Urbana, Illinois

Weekly seminar Aug 2013 - May 2014

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Journal Club

Urbana, Illinois

Weekly seminar 2013-2015

JULY 4, 2020 MILTON RUIZ · CURRICULUM 2

Grants/Allocations

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

CO-PI, HIGH-END COMPUTING RESOURCES NASA (\$2057)

Awarded: 4,291,380 SBUs

2018-2021

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

Co-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

Awarded: 3,404,828.0 SUs 2019-2020

Awarded: 750,000 node-hours (\$

465,500 usd) 2018-2019

CO-PI. BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Black Hole Formation on Cosmological Space-times

Awarded: \$ 16,500 usd 2014-2015

PI, Industrial University of Santander/Colciencias

Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers

Co-PI, RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Awarded: 500,000 node-hours

2017-2018

Studies In Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

usd)

Awarded: 3,000,000 SUs (\$145,539.34

2017-2018

Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

"Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Co-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 990,000 node-hours

2016-2017

Compact Object Binary Mergers: Simulations in Full General Relativity

CO-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (PHY100053)

Awarded 4,069,156 SUs (\$145,539.34

usd)

2014-2015

Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 610,000 node-hours

2013-2014

Electromagnetic Signatures of Neutron Star Binaries

PI, MARE NOSTRUM BSC ALLOCATION (FI-2011-3-0017)

Awarded: 120,000 core-hours (\$18,895,45,€)

2011-2012

Peer Reviewer/Referee ____

- Classical and Quantum Gravity
- Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society
- Physical Review D
- Physical Review Letters
- The Astrophysical Journal

Invited Talks/Panelist

Community Astrophysics Science with the Einstein Toolkit Code

Guadalajara, Mx

University of Guadalajara

Nov 20-24, 2017

Multimessenger astronomy: The new era of gravitational waves and electromagnetic Signatures

Jeju, Korea

COLLABORATIVE CONFERENCE ON GRAVITATIONAL WAVES

May 22-26, 2017

Gravitational Waves, a New Observational Window on the Universe

PHYSICS COLLOQUIUM, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col

May 16-19, 2016

Numerical relativity at the University of Santander

CELEBRATING ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF THE GENERAL RELATIVITY

Barranquilla, Col Nov 4-6, 2015

Numerical Solutions of the Einstein's field Equations

FIRST SYMPOSIUM ON RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSICS

Bucaramanga, Col June 10-12, 2015

The Cactus code and Numerical Relativity

NATIONAL ASTRONOMICAL OBSERVATORY, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col

Dec 16-20, 2006

Contributed Talks

Spinning binary neutron star mergers: Effects of the spin on jet outflows

28TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Allendale, Michigan, US

Oct 4-5, 2019

Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching

APS APRIL MEETING

Denver, Colorado, US

April 13-16, 2019

GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Maximum Mass

28TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Wisconsin-Milwaukee, US

Oct 12-13, 2018

Accretion Disks Around Supermassive Binary Black Holes: GRMHD Simulations of Postdecoupling and Merger

12TH INTERNATIONAL LISA SYMPOSIUM

Chicago, II, US

July 8-13, 2018

GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Maximum Mass

APS APRIL MEETING

Columbus, Ohio, US

April 14-17, 2018

GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets

27TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Ann Arbor, Michigan, US

Oct 12-14, 2017

Binary neutron star mergers as engines of short gamma-ray bursts: delayed vs. prompt collapse

APS APRIL MEETING

Washington, DC, US

Jan 28-31, 2017

MHD simulations of NSNS mergers in full GR: the role of the initial B field on the emergence of sGRB jets

APS APRIL MEETING

Salt Lake City, Utah, US

April 16-19, 2016

Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges

25TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Evanston, Il, US

Oct 1-3, 2015

Numerical Relativity: From Vacuum to Matter Spacetimes

THE 1ST COLOMBIA-ICRANET JULIO GARAVITO ARMERO MEETING

Bogotá-Bucaramanga, Col

Nov 23-27, 2015

Black Hole-Neutron Star Coalescence as engines that power sGRBs

SECOND WORKSHOP ON ASTRONOMY

Bogotá, Col July 27-31, 2015 Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges II

APS APRIL MEETING

Baltimore, Maryland, US April 11-14, 2015

Gravitational Waves as Probes of Dark Matter Spikes around Massive Black Holes

THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR

Urbana, Il, US Sep 3, 2014

General relativistic corrections to the pulsar spin-down luminosity

APS APRIL MEETING

Savannah, Georgia April 5-8, 2014

I-Love-Q Relations in Neutron Stars and their Applications to Astrophysics, Gravitational

Waves and Fundamental Physics

Urbana, Il, US

THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR

Feb 2, 2014

Initial boundary value problem of the Z4c formulation of General Relativity

23TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Evanston, Il, US Oct 25-26, 2013

The Initial Value Problem in General Relativity

CoCoNuT MEETING

Palma de Mallorca, Spain

High Order Outer Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation Oppurg, Germany

WORKSHOP ON NUMERICAL AND MATHEMATICAL RELATIVITY

Oct 11-13, 2012

Nov 26-28, 2012

Magnetospheres of compact objects in Force-Free Plasma

2ND IBERIAN GRAVITATIONAL WAVE MEETING

Barcelona, Spain

Constraint Preserving Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation

Workshop on Computational General Relativity

Province, Rhode Island, US

May 20-22, 2011

Feb 15-17, 2012

Constraint Preserving Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation of General Relativity

19TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON GENERAL RELATIVITY AND GRAVITATION

Mexico City, Mx

Oct 25-27, 2010

Refereed Publications

Ergostar models: where do they reside?

arXiv:2001.01473

A. Tsokaros, **M. Ruiz**, S.L. Shapiro

2020

Prospects for Fundamental Physics with LISA

E. BARAUSSE ET AL.

arXiv:2001.09793

Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations of Binary Neutron Star Mergers in General Relativity: Effects of Magnetic Field Orientation on Jet Launching

arXiv:2001.09153

M. Ruiz, A. Tsokaros, S.L. Shapiro

2020

The great impostors: Extremely compact, merging binary neutron stars in the mass gap posing as binary black holes

A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, L. Sun, S.L. Shapiro, K. Uryu

Phys. Rev. Lett. 124, 071101 (2020)

2019

Dynamically stable ergostars exist: General relativistic models and simulations

A. Tsokaros, M. Ruiz, L. Sun, S.L. Shapiro, K. Uryu

Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, 231103

2019

Enabling real-time multi-messenger astrophysics discoveries with deep learning

E. HUERTA ET AL.

Nature Reviews Physics 1, 600

2019

Effect of spin on the inspiral of binary neutron stars Phys.Rev. D100, 024061 A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S.L. SHAPIRO, K. URYU 2019 Are fast radio bursts the most likely electromagnetic counterpart of neutron star mergers Phys. Rev. D100, 043001 resulting in prompt collapse? V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz 2019 Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching Phys.Rev. D99, 084032 M. Ruiz, A. Tsokaros, V. Paschalidis, S.L. Shapiro, K. Uryu 2019 Magnetic Braking and Damping of Differential Rotation in Massive Stars Phys.Rev. D99, 064057 L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S.L. Shapiro 2019 Constant circulation sequences of binary neutron stars and their spin characterization Phys. Rev. D98, 124019 A. TSOKAROS, K. URYU, M. Ruiz, S.L. SHAPIRO Jet launching from binary black hole-neutron star mergers: Dependence on black hole Phys. Rev. D98, 123017 spin, binary mass ratio and magnetic field orientation M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, S.L. SHAPIRO 2018 Simulating the Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Incorporating Gas Phys. Rev. D98, 103008 **Pressure Perturbations and Different Rotation Profiles** L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S.L. Shapiro 2018 Disks Around Merging Binary Black Holes: From GW150914 to Supermassive Black Holes Phys. Rev. D97, 044036 A. Khan, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2018 GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Phys. Rev. D 97, 021501R **Maximum Mass** M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, A. Tsokaros The initial boundary value problem for free-evolution formulations of General Relativity Class. Ouan. Grav. 35 015006 D. HILDITCH, M. Ruiz GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets Phys. Rev. D 96, 084063 M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Black Hole Formation, Gravitational Phys. Rev. D 96, 043006 **Waves and Jets**

L. Sun, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2017

Gravitational wave content and stability of uniformly, rotating, triaxial neutron stars in Phys. Rev. D 95, 124057 general relativity

T. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, L. BAIOTTI, K. URYU 2017

Binary neutron star mergers: a jet engine for short gamma-ray bursts ApJ 824, L6 M. Ruiz, R. Lang, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro 2016

Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges ApJ 806, L14 V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2015

Accretion disks around binary black holes of unequal mass: GRMHD simulations of postdecoupling and merger
R. GOLD, V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO, Z. B. ETIENNE, H. PFEIFFER

Phys. Rev. D 90, 104030

2012

2012

2011

The Pulsar spin-down luminosity: simulations in general relativity

M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO

Phys. Rev. D 89, 084045

Almost-Killing conserved currents: a general mass function

M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, C. Bona.

Phys. Rev. D 89, 025011

Induced scalarization in boson stars and scalar gravitational radiation

M. Ruiz, J. C. Degollado, M. Alcubierre, D. Nunez, M. Salgado

Phys. Rev. D 86, 104044

The role of the ergosphere in the Blandford-Znajek process

M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, F. Galeazzi, C. Bona.

Mon. Not. R. Aston. Soc. 423

Constraint preserving boundary conditions for the Z4c formulation of general relativity

M. Ruiz, D. HILDITCH, S. BERNUZZI

Phys. Rev. D 83, 024025

Dynamic transition to spontaneous scalarization in boson stars Phys. Rev. D 81, 124018

M. Alcubierre J. C. Degollado, D. Nunez, **M. Ruiz**, M. Salgado

2010

Multipole expansions for energy and momenta carried by gravitational waves

M. Ruiz, M. Alcubierre, D. Nunez, R. Takahashi

Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 2467

2008

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric evolution codes in numerical relativity

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 159

Outer boundary conditions for Einstein's field equations in harmonic coordinates

M. Ruiz, O. RINNE, O. SARBACH

Class. Quant. Grav. 24, 6349

Conference Publications

Gravity and Light: Combining Gravitational Wave and Electromagnetic Observations in the 2020s

FERMILAB-PUB-19-169-AE

R. FOLEY ET AL.

2019

2019

Deep Learning for Multi-Messenger Astrophysics: A Gateway for Discovery in the Big Data

G. ALLEN ET AL.

arXiv:1902.00522

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric codes in numerical relativity

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

Rev. Mex. Fis. 53, 144

Computer Skills _____

Operating Systems: UNIX, Linux, Windows, Mac OS X

Programming Language: FORTRAN, C, C++

Document Preparation LaTeX, Microsoft Office, Open/Libre Office

Other: Bash scripting, Basic system administration

Languages ____

Spanish (native speaker)

English

Primary References _____

Professor Miguel Alcubierre

Departamento de Gravitación y Teoría de Campos Instituto de Ciencias Nucleares UNAM Mexico City, Mexico malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx +55 562-33-371 Ext. 3371

Professor Sebastiano Bernuzzi

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut Friedrich-Schiller-Universitaät Jena Jena, Germany sebastiano.bernuzzi@uni-jena.de +49 (0)3641 9 47111

Professor Vasileios Paschalidis

Astronomy and Physics Departments University of Arizona Tucson, Arizona, US vpaschal@email.arizona.edu +1 520-621-9643

Professor Stuart L. Shapiro

Department of Physics University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Urbana, Il, US slshapir@illinois.edu +1 217-333-5427